Finding Aid for Jay A. Bolt Papers 1931-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jay A. Bolt papers 1931-1998 1949-1981
Bolt, Jay A. (1911- )
9668 Aa 2
Professor of Mechanical Engineering at the University of Michigan, papers consist of course materials and publications by Bolt.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These papers were donated by Jay A. Bolt (donor no. 8395 ) in August 1995
The collection is open for research.
A professor of mechanical engineering at the University of Michigan, Jay A. Bolt was born on October 31, 1911. He received a bachelor of science in mechanical engineering degree from Michigan State University in 1934. He also received a masters in engineering from there in 1947. In between he was awarded a master of mechanical engineering degree from the Chrysler Institute and a master of science degree from Purdue University. He was an instructor in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan in 1937-38. He rejoined the faculty in 1947 as an associate professor. Prior to that he had taught at the University of Illinois and Notre Dame University. Bolt lectured extensively on the internal combustion engine and was professor in charge of the auto lab from 1970 to 1980. He was also a consultant to the automobile industry. In addition to his teaching and research in the auto lab, he did research with several aviation firms studying engine design and fuel flow problems in aircraft. He was also concerned with the use of computers in engineering education. He retired from the university in 1982.
These papers are arranged into five series:
Examinations
Lecture Notes
Photographs
Problem Sets
Publications
The Jay A. Bolt papers consist primarily of course materials for mechanical engineering classes he taught in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1931-1985 and publications by Bolt. The course material includes lecture notes, examinations, and problem sets and photographs. Much of the material is arranged by course number within these series. The researcher using this collection should be aware of certain course number changes. Four major changes affect this collection. They are Mechanical Engineering (hereafter ME) 114 changing to ME 496, ME 155 to ME 497, ME 105 to ME 235, and ME 214 to ME 594
Subjects:
Bolt, Jay A.; Mechanical engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Examinations
  Examinations (.8 linear ft.) contains tests and answer sheets from 1949 to 1982. On some examinations Bolt wrote notes about the length of the answer or the amount of thought he hoped that the questions would provoke from students. This series also contains some undated material from the period when Bolt taught at Notre Dame.
  - ME 105 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - ME 114 1949-1961, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - ME 115 1949 (Box 1)
  - ME 160 1947-1952, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - ME 214
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - ME 235
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
  - ME 333 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - ME 335
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - ME 496
    - 1960-1974, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - ME 497 1977 (Box 1)
  - ME 594 1963-1975 (Box 1)
  - Notre Dame undated (Box 1)
- Lecture Notes
  Lecture Notes (2.4 linear ft) contains private notes and material distributed to students from 1931 to 1985. It is not in strict chronological order because Bolt would reuse some material from year to year. It is arranged by course number and then by chapter number of the text used in the course. In addition, there are some excerpts from published texts.
  - The Atom 1940-1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Building the Modern World 1954 (Box 1)
  - Concerning Engine Indicator Diagrams 1957 (Box 1)
  - Ford 1957 (Box 2)
  - ME 26 and 32 undated (Box 2)
  - ME 105 1949 (Box 2)
  - ME 106 Schedules 1956-1962 (Box 2)
  - ME 114 1956-1962
    - Introduction-Chapter 3 1949-1977 (Box 2)
    - Obert
      - Chapter 1-7 1931-1965 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 8-12 1948-1970 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 13-15 1949-1957 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 16-17 1949-1963 (Box 2)
  - ME 115 1949 (Box 2)
  - ME 214
    - 1952-1959 (Box 2)
    - Combustion 1952-1961 (Box 2)
    - Engine Balance undated (Box 2)
    - Schedule 1952-1959 (Box 2)
  - ME 235
    - Chapter 1-2 1949-1981 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 3-5 1958-1981 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 6-7 1956-1981 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 8-9 1956-1977 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 10-11 1931-1977 (Box 2)
    - Schedule 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - ME 255
    - PROJ C 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Sterling Original Data 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - ME 496
    - 1st Meeting 1962-1980 (Box 2)
    - Bolt Chapter 1-6 1965-1981 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 1 1950-1980 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 2 1950-1975 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 3-5 1949-1980 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 6 1949-1970 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 7 1950-1980 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 12 1963-1980 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 14 1949-1979 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 15 1958-1985 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 16 1952-1974 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 18-20 1951-1980 (Box 3)
    - Obert Book
      - Chapter 1-8 1949-1977 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 9-12 1951-1977 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 13-17 1949-1977 (Box 3)
    - Schedule 1964 (Box 3)
    - Volume 2, Chapter 2 1969-1980 (Box 3)
  - ME 497
    - 1st Meeting- Chapter 1 1947-1980 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 2-4 1947-1966 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 5 1948-1964 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 5a 1956-1961 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 6 1950-1965 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 7 1959-1964 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 8-10b 1941-1976 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 11 1959-1964 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 13 1947-1963 (Box 3)
    - Chapter 14-19 1957-1978 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1980 (Box 3)
    - Measurement Instruments 1957-1973 (Box 3)
    - Organization 1959-1973 (Box 3)
  - ME 594
    - 1952-1975, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Chapter 1-20 1963, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Schedule 1975 (Box 4)
    - Thermo et al. 1961-1974, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Photographs
  Photographs (.1 linear ft.) consists of pictures of classes taken by Bolt to help him identify the students in his class.
  - ME 497 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - ME 235 undated (Box 4)
  - Photograph of Bolt and his wife 1998 (Box 4)
- Problem Sets
  Problem Sets (.6 linear ft) contains assignments and solutions from 1949 to 1981. Its arrangement is very similar to Lecture Notes with course numbers and then chapter numbers.
  - ME 105 1949 (Box 4)
  - ME 115 1949 (Box 4)
  - ME 235
    - English Units
      - Chapter 2-8 1962-1976 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 9-12 1957-1959 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 13-16 1956-1960 (Box 4)
    - Metric Units
      - Chapter 1-5 1975-1978 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 6-11 1975-1981 (Box 4)
  - ME 496
    - 1964 (Box 4)
    - Obert, 2nd Edition
      - Chapter 2-10 1950-1960 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 11-17 undated (Box 4)
    - Bolt
      - Chapter 3-4 1954-1974 (Box 4)
      - Chapter 6, 12 undated (Box 4)
    - Obert, 3rd Edition 1937-1977 (Box 4)
    - Taylor and Taylor 1962-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - ME 498 undated (Box 4)
  - ME 594
    - 1953-1975 (Box 4)
    - Old Material 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Project on Computers in Engineering Education, Problem 1-9, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Publications
  Publications (.1 linear ft) contains published material written by Professor Bolt.
  - Diesel Fuel Injection system Stimulation and Experimental Corrosion, 1974 (Box 4)
  - A preliminary Literature Survey of the of the Fuel Metering and induction Processes for Spark Ignited Energy, 1958 (Box 4)
The researcher is also referred to the Walter E. Lay Papers. Professor Bolt was a close friend and colleague of Walter Lay.